so this is from the DAP part this verse
one mind precedes all
phenomenon mind is their leader and
their maker if one speaks or acts with a
corrupt mind suffering follows from that
as a wheel follows the ox's
hoof so the question is what does it
mean that mind precedes all things all
phenomena what is a corrupt mind mind
and why does it give rise to suffering
so in simple terms um mind precedes all
things simply means that pretty much
anything that you can experience
perceive know
remember plan anything that can manifest
in any shape or form in any sense
imaginary doesn't matter
how uh requires the mind requires the
mind to be there requires requires you
to be
conscious so in that sense you can't
even fathom you can't even
imagine things on their
own standing in the world on their own
without you're you being aware of
them CU like even that imagination is
something that your mind precedes and
enables it to
do
so in that sense mind comes first not
like mind can stand on its
own you like in order to be conscious
there needs to be something to be
conscious of but
of but
uh Consciousness on its own cannot stand
mind on its own cannot
stand mind Mano needs it its objects
needs its counterparts that Define it
but those counterparts would not exist
without that
mind so that's what it means mind comes
first corrupt mind is the Mind affected
with greed desire
greed desire
sensuality ill will
indolence uh mind that's uh that's uh
that doesn't have
perspective mind that entertains
ownership of
things mind that assumes contradictions
such as things existing outside of
it um to name one and so and so so and
the other that that the idea
that mind is the well this mind precedes
all things and some people think mind is
eternal and stands independent of all
things so that's another Corruption of
Mind exactly yeah yeah thinking that the
mind can can stand on its own you know
like you hear the teachings like the
pure mind um uh even like pure
Consciousness that's independent of the
Aggregates and stuff that's complete
nonsense that's that's that's a
fantasy imagination that there and then
is something you're conscious of and
your mind predes and you're aware of it
but see you you gave it the significance
of it being more than it is oh there is
this great mind outside of things or
there is this great reality outside of
this mind either way you're overshooting
the mark you're not seeing the
dependence between the mind and Damas
mind and phenomenal they exist to the
same extent in as much one defines the
other the other one defines the former
one so it's like uh it's the
relationship that the sarut used in the
sutas to describe namarupa and Viana
Viana namarupa like two sticks
supporting each other none of them can
remain standing without the other one
and neither of them stands more than the
other one so so to speak so yeah those
would all be the Corruptions of the mind
but see regardless of what corrupted
wrong views you might have all of those
views uh get their fuel From
Desire from
Delight from aversion and from
distraction and
indolence if you were to not give into
those basic
contradictions of sensual desire ill
will and distraction
delusion uh the views would diminish
however wrong they were before they
would diminish the fuel their intensity
in other words you would be uh removing
the dust from your eyes kind of almost
unknowingly so to speak if you are
purifying your mind from greed diversion
and delusion you are
removing simply you're removing the
fertile ground for the proliferation of
the wrong views so you might still have
some wrong views left but you would not
have as many and those that are left
probably would not be as solidified and
strong as as the ones that still have
that vast amount of fuel of desire and
sensuality and so
on so that's those are the Corruptions
of the mind and um so you could see then
with mind affected with desire anything
you perceive smell taste touch remember
perceive smell taste touch remember
imagine
anything paired with a corrupt mind
standing there together with a corrupt
mind mind it's going to be
distorted it's not going to be uh
understood it's not going to be seen
correctly and that Distortion is
manifested uh through things like
ownership conceit
sensuality so if you sense of self as
well yeah so basically if you have like
if say oh do I do I regard things as
mine do I have desire to sense objects
is my sense of self is my conceit still
there all of those are symptoms of that
corruption still being there fueled or
to fueled to some extent maybe not the
same for all people but if those things
exist in your
experience they are the indicators that
the corrupt mind is still there
um and you haven't addressed it fully
because you can't possibly have an
uncorrupt mind and have a sense of self
uncorrupt mind and have a desire to
attent objects uncorrupt mind and have a
conceit or real will impossible
inconceivable so and then why that
results in suffering well because
presence of craving in your experience
in any shape or form on any level means
presence of suffering to that
extent not more not
less doesn't mean suffering will come
later even if it does it means
immediately simply the presence of a of
of of of a mind corrupted through
craving thus the presence of craving
means presence of suffering means
presence of
unease so even if you say oh I don't
suffer about anything currently there's
nothing bothering me I'm quite
happy if you dig deep even within that
happy experience there and then while
it's present you would see that the
overall framework of that experience is
certain uneasiness certain certain implication
uneasiness certain certain implication
of their lack of control anxiety and so
on now obviously when things are
Pleasant you focus on what's in front of
you so you you ignore that very
framework but if you are honest you
would see that it is very much still
there so even in your greatest moments
of Happiness if your mind is not
uncorrupted from those from those three
Corruptions uh means fundamentally you
are still very much within the domain of
suffering because Dua is measured by
that it's measured by the degree of
uneasiness so whether it's sometimes a
subtle uneasiness or a coarse one or a
full-blown anxiety it's the same thread
of the same dooka of the presence of the
same craving of the same corrupt
mind so it's not like oh
um I am directly
responsible for the presence of craving
in my mind so I will choose not to Crave
and that's how mind will stop to crave
it's not that easy it's more like things
that I do on this indirect level sight
sound smell taste touches ideas I I
repeatedly engage with with Desire with
delight with ill will with aversion that
keeps my mind
corrupted corrupted mind is affected
with craving
presence of that craving in that
corrupted mind is why I feel suffering
over here so you could say you are the
here so you could say you are the
victim of craving for which you
indirectly basically inadvertently
almost responsible you're fueling it
unknowingly so there you go mind
precedes all things comes first
I.E if you are paired with an uncorrupt
mind everything will be uncorrupted if
you're paided with a corrupted mind
everything will be distorted and
corrupted mind is corrupted through GED
of verion delusion and mind such mind
causes suffering because that's what uh
basically that's where the craving
exists in such a mind that's where the
craving can only exist craving can only
exist in in a corrupted mind so presence
of craving means presence of
suffering